Guide to the Rob Amberg Sodom Laurel Album Exhibit Photographs, 1975-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rob Amberg Sodom Laurel Album Exhibit photographs 1975-1994 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies.
3.0 linear feet Extent: 16 Items
Documentary photographer and writer based in western North Carolina. Collection contains 16 gelatin silver prints from Amberg's Sodom Laurel Album book that the Center for Documentary Studies turned into a traveling exhibit. Also includes 32 prints displayed in the Allen Building exhibition. Acquired as part of the Archive for Documentary Arts.
RL.01237
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted to educational, non-commercial use. Creator retains all copyrights.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Rob Amberg Sodom Laurel Album Exhibit Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2011.
Biographical Note
Rob Amberg's photographs and writings have been exhibited and published nationally and internationally in journals, magazines, and galleries. He lectures frequently and performs regular documentary assignments for non-profit organizations, philanthropic foundations and editorial publications. He is the recipient of fellowships and awards from numerous organizations, including: the National Endowment for the Humanities, the John Simon Guggenheim Foundation, the Center for Documentary Studies, Alternate Roots, the North Carolina Humanities Council, and the National Endowment for the Arts.
His book, Sodom Laurel Album, was published in 2002 by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University and the University of North Carolina Press. The book received the 2003 Thomas Wolfe Memorial Literary Award from the Western North Carolina Historical Association. In 2005, his work was included in the book Quartet: Four North Carolina Photographers, which was published by Safe Harbor Books. His latest book, The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress, was published in 2009 by the Center for American Places and the University of Georgia Press.
Dellie Chandler Norton (1898-1993) was a much-loved storyteller and ballad singer whose songs were recorded by Alan Lomax and John Cohen. In 1990, she received a North Carolina Folk Heritage Award.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of 2 series, each holding prints from Amberg's Sodom Laurel Album, first published by the University of North Carolina Press in 2002. Acquired as part of the Archive for Documentary Arts.
The 16 gelatin silver prints in the Traveling Exhibit series were used in a 2003 traveling exhibit created by the Center for Documentary Studies. The series includes images of Dellie Norton and her family, tobacco planters and workers, and scenes from Madison County, North Carolina.
The 32 Allen Building Exhibit prints were used in an exhibition at Duke University's Allen Building. They include both 11x14 and 16x20 gelatin silver prints. Scenes include Dellie Norton and her family, tobacco workers, cemeteries, and folk arts.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Amberg, Rob; Amberg, Rob -- Sodom Laurel Album; Norton, Dellie Chandler; Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; Tobacco farmers -- North Carolina -- Madison County; Tobacco farmers -- North Carolina -- Madison County -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; Southern States -- Social Conditions; Country life -- North Carolina -- Pictorial works; North Carolina -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints
Related Material
The Rob Amberg Photographs collection in Duke University's Archive for Documentary Arts has photographs from the same project.
Contents of Collection
- Sodom Laurel Album Traveling Exhibit, (2 boxes)
  Box 1 contains 11x14 prints; Box 2 contains 16x20 prints. Includes the page number from Sodom Laurel Album.
  - Junior and the jumping cat, 1975 (page 15) (Box 1)
  - Junior with hoe and my Shadow, 1975-1978 (page 83)
  - Dellie's sister Berzilla Wallin holding a picture of the Wallin family band (page 114)
  - Mary Norton, Dellie's youngest daughter, 1977 (page 78)
  - Junior, holding ginseng root, 1975-1978 (page 93)
  - Junior holding the Hippie from Mississippi picture, 1984 (page 99)
  - Warehouse worker unloading tobacco that's been purchased for shipment to a factory, 1981 (page 110)
  - K. Stark, a tobacco buyer for the Western Tobacco Company, bidding on a crop of tobacco (page 109)
  - Janice Rice, Dellie's grandson Larry's ex-wife, waiting for her tobacco check, Planter's Warehouse, Asheville, 1994 (page 112)
  - Dellie's Aunt Zipporah Rice at home, Rice Cove, 1976 (page 117)
  - Film crew working on a scene for the movie Amazing Grace: America in song, on Dellie's porch, 1975 (page 84)
  - Tildie making strawberry jam at her place on Caney Fork, 1994 (page 51) (Box 2)
  - Driving to Sodom through Walnut Gap and over Walnut Mountain (page 1)
  - Dellie, topping and suckering her tobacco, 1976 (page 31)
  - Dellie walking out to the porch, 1993 (page 141)
  - Junior at Dellie's funeral, Marshall, 1993 (page 143)
- Sodom Laurel Album Allen Building Exhibit, (2 boxes)
  Box 3 contains 11x14 matted prints; Box 4 contains 16x20 matted prints. Includes the page number from Sodom Laurel Album.
  - On Dellie's porch, Sodom Laurel, 1978 (page 85) (Box 3)
  - Dellie doing laundry on the side porch, undated (page 11)
  - Doug Wallin sowing his tobacco seed bed, undated (page 24)
  - Tilman Chandler's barn and tobacco, Ben Cove, 1975 (page 28)
  - Clinton Norton waiting for the bus on the first day of school, undated (page 38)
  - Dellie playing a game of Setback with Marthie, Junior, and Joe, 1977 (page 79)
  - Warehouse workers unloading tobacco, Planters Warehouse, 1981 (page 106)
  - Berzilla buck dancing on stage at teh North Carolina bicentennial Folklife Festival, Eno River State Park, Durham, 1976 (page 121)
  - The Annual Rice Cove Cemetery grave decoration: praying, 1976 (page 128)
  - The Annual Rice Cove Cemetery grave decoration: singing, 1977 (page 128)
  - Dellie at her ninetieth birthday at the Jesuit residence, Hot Springs, 1988 (page 136)
  - Junior repairing the spring, 1976 (page 12)
  - Junior and Pet, 1978 (page 17)
  - Clinton Norton and Junior on Dellie's porch, undated (page 40)
  - Joyce Chandler, Joe Ross's wife, in the living room of Marthie and Joe's trailer, Ben Cove, 1976 (page 45)
  - Dellie holding a photograph of her father, Mart Chandler, 1993 (page 131)
  - Isaac Gunter's tobacco plant bed and cemetery, 1982 (page 2) (Box 4)
  - Junior walking to the house from the barn, undated (page 4)
  - Outside at Dellie's: the shed and the pear tree behind the house, 1977-1978 (page 13)
  - Dellie and Junior, 1978 (page 14)
  - Junior plowing ground with Pet, undated (page 23)
  - McKinley Massey family and neighbors carrying tobacco plants to the field for planting, undated (page 27)
  - Hispanic migrant farm workers hauling sticks of tobacco, Upper Brush Creek, 1993 (page 65)
  - Angie and Juanita Shelton unloading tobacco, The Shelton's barn, Hopewell, 1983 (page 68)
  - Dellie and her cow Pet in the barn with tobacco curing overhead, Burton Cove, 1977 (page 70)
  - The family on the porch, undated (page 85, and Cover)
  - Junior taking a picture of Dellie and David Holt, holding his son Zeb, in her front yard, 1978 (page 99)
  - Dellie tying the leaves into hands, 1976 (page 104)
  - Doug Wallin fiddling in the living room, Craine Branch, 1977 (page 123)
  - Dellie looking fierce in her living room at the lower house, 1986 (page 141)